I wanted to show you another
example of an unbounded Petri net.
What we have here before is
not yet an unbounded Petri net.
This is a bounded Petri net.
We know that because we
had already drawn a reachability graph
for it on the slides, and it was finite.
And that means per se
that the Petri net is bounded.
Let me remind you again:
What was possible here?
So, in the initial situation (the reachability graph
also specified this), exactly only t1 was fireable
and would then lead to the fact
that we ultimately have two tokens down here.
Because of this 2 here.
And after that,
there were several possibilities.
We could fire t2, fire t3.
We could also fire t2 and fire
t2, or fire t3 and fire t3.
Then in some of these
constellations, we reached a dead end.
So the Petri net was not deadlock-free.
But that is not the point at the moment.
Let's just first take the path that
leads to ending up
back at the initial marking.
So that would be executing t2,
t3 or t3, t2 in any order.
And the Petri net is bounded, that can
be intuitively explained here (beyond the fact that
you can just set up the
reachability graph) by the fact that
at each transition, there are
as many tokens consumed as generated.
Yes, we see that both
here and here, for example.
So there are two tokens going
in and two tokens coming out.
But that's also true for the
other transitions in this particular Petri net.
And therefore, a simple way to
get an unbounded Petri net here is
that we replace, for example,
this 2 with a 3.
Yes, this is still a Petri net,
but a different one with different weights.
A different mathematical formulation
would also have that.
And then we can look:
What would happen now?
And, well, I have just made
sure that the number of tokens
in the system can increase, and
can increase constantly, again and again.
Just increasing the number of tokens
once would not lead to unboundedness.
But here we have now that, for example, when
firing t1, one token is consumed from the left,
one token is consumed from the right,
and three tokens are deposited at the bottom.
Then the next constellation
would look like this.
And that's one that didn't show
up yet in the earlier reachability graph,
because the Petri net
has now changed here.
And now it would be possible
to fire on in different ways.
Among other things, one way to
continue would be that we move
up this token, for example, then move this
token to here, and then fire t1 again.
What would happen then?
Then again a token would
disappear from here, a token
would disappear from here, and three tokens
would be put down at the bottom.
Because of this 3, which is
at the output arrow for t1.
That could then look
like this, for example.
And then you can already see that you can
ultimately reach any number of tokens
here on place s3, for example.
Not only on place s3.
We can also move them all
up to s2 or to s1.
Here it is even true that for each
place in this Petri net and each constant
c that we choose, for example
15, we can still have 16 tokens
lying on a position, for example,
after a sufficient number of firing operations.
That is, the constant c = 15 does
not bound the behavior of this Petri net.
And even if we choose some
higher constant c, for example 37,
then there are also firing
processes, which at some point lead
to 38 tokens or more
lying on at least one place.
I hope that's clear basically as far as
I've developed it here,
that that can happen.
So for example, I could now fire up here.
And now I could fire t1 here
again with these two tokens, and then
I would already have six tokens lying
at the bottom on the s3 place afterwards.
And that is not bounded.
Yes, so 6 would still be bounded, but
7, 8, 9, 10 etc. are also possible.
That means, in the end, you can accumulate
as many tokens as you like on individual places.
And thus, by definition, the
Petri net is not bounded.
Of course it is not 1-safe.
It is not anyway, already because
of the 2 that was there.
But it is also not bounded
for any other arbitrarily high constant.
It is interesting that such unboundedness does
not necessarily have to come from the fact
(like here) that we have
such weights greater than 1.
So there are also Petri nets, which
fulfill so to speak the first
condition of 1-safety (namely each weight is
at most 1 and in the start
marking even on each place lies at
most one token), and nevertheless such
a Petri net can be unbounded then.
You might think about this on your own.
Think about a Petri net which
looks syntactically good at first (no
weights greater than 1, no places of
the start marking with more than one token),
and yet the Petri net is not bounded.
This is not the example you see here.
You could think of
a suitable example yourself.
This is quite instructive, I think.